It's that time once again. Another major
Magic the Gathering tournament. Another
round of viewers, Reddit, and Twitter
screaming that somebody cheated. So, in
today's video, I'll answer the question,
did the winner of the Magic the
Gathering World Championship cheat their
way to victory? So, this all happened in
the 31st MTG World Championship in
December, where, spoilers, Hall of Famer
Seth Manfield won his second World
Championship title. But unfortunately,
his win was marred by two incidents
during his quarterfinal match against
Ken Yukahiro. I'm going to show both
clips first, then I'll discuss them
afterwards. The first clip takes us
midway through the second match in a
best of five in the quarterfinals.
>> That's not going to get it done, right?
>> Does have the mana
>> because of that. Yeah. Well, because of
the mana. And then it won't work on He's
going to name Spider here, which also
does protect Superior Spider-Man,
>> right?
>> It does not for Ardan.
Human would cover both.
>> I'm not going to do that. Um, you said
spider on this. Uh, you can still cast
it though, right?
>> I mean, he can't take that.
>> You can't.
>> Wow.
>> You can still cast a counter spell on
him.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, it's pretty obvious what happened
there for those familiar with cards in
standard right now. Ken plays Cavern of
Souls and names Spiders. The land lets
Ken cast uncounterable creatures of the
chosen type. He then goes to cast brood
spinner, a spider, using the cavern of
souls mana, and then Seth goes to cast
the counter spell, it'll quench her,
which of course would do nothing in this
situation.
Seth quickly realizes this and then
performs something that we in the
industry call a takes back seas. Most
commonly performed at your casual
commander games. Much to the shock of
the commentators, the judge appears to
allow this. The game continues and Seth
will eventually win this game.
The next clip happens in the following
game. In game three of the best of five,
we're in the late stages of the game and
Seth is down to four cards in his
library. He has just cast Monument to
Endurance, an artifact that can draw
cards, create treasures, and most
importantly, make opponents lose three
life. He also has some artist talents in
play to help trigger the monument. Let's
play the clip.
>> Okay. What is Ken at? 13.
>> He's at 13 life. That's That's five
triggers. That's five cards. You have to
rummage five times. Um,
what is going on here?
>> He does have Stormchaser's talent.
>> Okay, you get to reset the monument
here, right? B, by boomerang basics.
>> And he needs to do three life like every
chance he can get, right?
>> So, he rummages off of this, drains your
opponent for three, pick it up, then you
can replay it. Don't rummage off the
artist talent, of course, and then cast
another spell. But, he doesn't have
enough cards left in his deck unless he
finds the second monument to endurance.
Is this for real right now? But remember
the bottom.
>> Can I take this back or
>> I don't I already cast it.
>> Well, you can't take this back. Come on
now.
>> He He cast it.
>> Okay.
>> What?
>> You have how many cards in hand?
>> One.
>> Wait. So, he didn't cast a boomerang
basics now.
>> I guess he didn't.
>> Wow. Why?
>> That is all right. So,
>> so of the two, this is clearly the most
egregious clip. Seth taps mana for
boomerang basics, clearly indicates that
the monument to endurance is the target,
and then proceeds to go into the tank
for around 30 seconds before eventually
saying,
>> "Can I take this [music] back?
>> Can I take this back?" Mentioning to the
judge that he already cast the spell.
The judge does say something. It's very
hard to make out over the commentators,
but allows Seth to perform a takes these
back seas again much to the shock of a
commentators and Twitch chat. Okay, so
did Seth break any rules here? In short,
absolutely not. Firstly, reversing
decisions is allowed by the Magic
Tournament rules. If we take a look at
section 4.8, Eight. It tells us
sometimes a player will realize that
they have made a wrong decision after
making a play. If that player has not
gained any information since taking the
action and they wish to make a different
decision, a judge may allow that player
to change their mind.
It goes on to say, "Judges must
carefully consider whether the player
has gained information since making the
play that might have affected the
decision." In particular, players may
not try to use opponent's reactions or
lack thereof to see if they should
modify actions they committed to. Now, a
[snorts] lot of people are pointing to
this line here, stating that it looks
like Seth waited until Ken said, "Okay."
before quickly requesting a takeback,
indicating that this is a reaction that
Seth was looking for. It's worth
pointing out that at this level of play,
the tournament is using open deck lists.
Seth is aware of what Ken is running in
his Sultai Reanimator deck. It is a
primarily sorcery speed deck and the two
instance that Ken could have are either
not playable or not applicable to this
situation. You could argue that Ken
could have had a bitter triumph, but
even then this isn't really the point at
which you would cast the spell and even
then it is not relevant to the situation
at hand. Boomerang Basics is a sorcery
targeting an [music] artifact. Now, the
MTR does happen to give three examples
of takebacks that would be allowed.
Playing a land and then quickly changing
that decision, declaring no blocks
against an attacker and then immediately
changing their mind, and passing the
turn and then suddenly wanting to not
pass the turn and take a game action.
All three of these examples are painted
as quick changes of mind and not I'll
make an action then wait 30 seconds
before changing my mind.
I think the first clip is a pretty
reasonable example of a takeback in line
with what is laid out in the MTR.
Having said that, nowhere in section 4.8
does it mention that a player only has a
certain number of seconds to think about
their decision before they can reverse
it. After all, this isn't touch chess.
So, having said all that, again, did
Seth break any rules? Absolutely not.
Was this sloppy play for someone playing
at World Championships?
Maybe. As I've said in previous videos,
playing at these tournaments for
multiple days is mentally draining and
taxing. Not to mention the pressure of
the prize money on the line. I think the
most important thing to point out and
stress is that Seth did exactly the
right thing here. And I think this is
the biggest lesson everybody should take
away from the video. Seth called a
judge. He turned and asked the judge,
"Can I take this back?" and explained
the situation. It was very clear and out
in the open. At this point, the judge
could have easily said no and told him
to play on, but obviously that's not
what happened. Now, did the judge make
the right call here? I would say so.
It's definitely riding a thin line on
what is written in the tournament rules
versus what is probably intended. The
rules are allowing for quick fixes of
decisions, not letting players tank on a
decision presented on a board. As I've
mentioned in another video of mine, if
you ever find yourself presented with a
decision from a judge that you think is
incorrect, you can always appeal to the
head judge. Just remember though that
the head judge's decision is final.
It's tough to say whether this rule's
incident is going to force a change of
section 4.8. At the end of the day, it
feels like the rule is there to protect
those playing at every level but
professional. After all, the rules
enforcement level for worlds is set to
professional, which means these
tournaments hold players to a higher
standard of behavior and technically
correct play than competitive
tournaments.
Perhaps wizards will make a change in
the near future. What do you think? Let
me know in the comments down below. As
always, if you learned something, be
sure to like the video and subscribe
because if you don't, I'm [music] going
to take these back seas this video.
Thanks for watching and I'll see you in
the next